F. Coulton Waugh Papers
F. Coulton Waugh Papers
1830-1971
Waugh, Coulton, 1896-1973.
3.33 linear ft.
Papers of the British born painter, cartoonist, illustrator, lithographer, engraver, textile designer, writer. Collection includes artwork, maps, printed material, photographs, textiles, writings and drawings of Coulton Waugh, wife Elizabeth Waugh, grandfather, portrait painter Samuel Bell Waugh, and father, marine artist Frederick Judd Waugh.
148738
Biographical History
Frederick Coulton Waugh (1896-1973) was a British born artist, cartoonist, textile designer, and author.
Coulton Waugh was born on March 10, 1896 in Cornwall, England. He was the third generation of artistic Waughs. His grandfather, Samuel Bell Waugh, was a prosperous portrait painter in Philadelphia. His father, Frederick Judd Waugh, was a distinguished marine painter.
In 1907 the Waugh family moved to America. Coulton studied at the Art Students League in New York with George Bridgeman, Frank Dumond and John Carlson. By 1916 Coulton was making his living by textile designing. In 1918 he married Elizabeth Jenkinson and three years later the couple moved to Provincetown, Massachusetts. There they operated a model ship and hooked rug shop for eleven years.
Coulton Waugh has written the book Painting With a Knife and numerous other articles on painting and painting techniques. He has exhibited his works at the National Academy of Design and Carnegie Institute and his paintings can be found in the permanent collections of museums in Iowa, Ohio and New York.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The F. Coulton Waugh Papers are arranged in seven series: Artwork, Biographical Data, Family, Photographs, Printed Material and Writings. The collection includes material about Waugh and his family. A portion of the items in this collection are dated according to F. Coulton Waugh's description of the items.
The Artwork (circa 1908-1932) series consists of different types of work done by Waugh, including illustrations, postcards, prints, and magazine cover designs.
The Biographical Data (undated) series contains Waugh's own notes on his life and explanations of specific items contained in this collection.
The Family (1896-1953) series contains work from Waugh's wife, Elizabeth Waugh, his father, Frederick Judd Waugh, and his grandfather, Samuel Bell Waugh. From Elizabeth Waugh there is her book Collecting Hooked Rugs, from 1927, and some background from F. Coulton Waugh. There are original drawings from Frederick Judd Waugh, including some drawings from Cornwall, England (1896-1906), Ex-Libris drawing (1898) and an article from Look magazine (1953). Samuel Bell Waugh's original artwork is from around 1830.
The Photographs series (1881-1966) includes some family portraits and photos. A large portion of the series contains photos from F. Coulton Waugh's Provincetown Period (1921-1932), including his house that was originally built in 1740 and described as the "oldest home in Provincetown."
Printed Material (1919-1969) consists of newspaper excerpts, posters, textile designs and a large collection of maps and prints of ships. Designed maps include the locations of: Cape Cod; Florida; Saint Pauls School in Concord; New Hampshire; Parts Unknown; the Hudson River; New York, Long Island and the Coast of Connecticut. While the majority of the map reproductions have Coulton Waugh's signature, some of the map prints and assortment of ship prints may be not be designed by Waugh. There are also some notes from Waugh about specific items.
Writings (1913-1928) contains Waugh's personal notebook from 1913 to 1919, notes on navigation, and Motivations a typed work by Waugh.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Collecting Hooked Rugs by Elizabeth Waugh was removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books.
Radical Views by Russell Brandt was removed from the collection and transferred to the
American Radicalism Ephemera
collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Literature -- American Fiction; Waugh, Coulton, 1896-1973.; Waugh, Frederick Judd, 1861-1940.; Waugh, Samuel Bell.; Waugh, Elizabeth Dey Jenkinson, 1894-1944.; Art, Modern -- 19th century -- United States.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Illustrators -- United States.; Lithographers -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Drawings (visual works); Photographs.; Diaries.; Maps (documents); Notes (documents); Textiles.; Artists.; Cartoonists.; Illustrators.; Lithographers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of F. Coulton Waugh, 1969-1970
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Arts and Decoration cover design, 1921; includes cover and magazine (Box 1)
  - Caricatures of German leaders, circa Oct 1918; original drawings (Oversize 2)
  - Drawings, Montclair Period, 1908-1915 (Box 1)
  - Drawings, Montclair Period 1908-1915 (Oversize 1)
  - McClure's magazine, 1921; black and white reproductions (Box 1)
  - Postcards and prints, 1921-1932; Oldest House in Provincetown, Mass.; some done by Waugh (Box 1)
- Biographical data
  - Undated, background information about the collection (Box 1)
- Family
  - Elizabeth Waugh
    - Collecting Hooked Rugs by Elizabeth Waugh, circa 1927; Item located in Rare Books.; includes description from F.C. Waugh
  - Frederick Judd Waugh
    - Drawings, circa 1896-1906; St. Ives, Cornwall, England (Box 2)
    - Ex-Libris, 1898 (Oversize 1)
    - Look magazine article, 1953 (Oversize 1)
  - Samuel Bell Waugh
    - Drawings, circa 1830 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Boating Life-Provincetown, Mass., 1921-1932; includes folder of photos (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Waugh photo, circa 1921-1932 (Oversize 1)
  - Family, 1881-1938; 1898,; 1966; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hooked Rugs, undated; includes photos & rug description (Box 1)
  - Oldest House in Provincetown, Mass., 1921-1932; includes photo album (Box 1)
  - Provincetown, Mass., 1921-1932; includes photos (Box 1)
  - Provincetown Photos, circa 1934 (Oversize 1)
- Printed material
  - The Art News, Jan 16 1932; includes additional excerpt (Oversize 1)
  - Boston Sunday Post, Aug 30 1930 (Oversize 1)
  - Framed newspaper collage, circa May 1932 (Oversize 1)
  - Hooked Rugs, 1933; includes posters and New York Sun Apr 29 1933 article (Box 1)
  - Magazine reproductions of Waugh textiles, 1919-1920 (Oversize 1)
  - Maps - newspaper and magazine reproductions, 1922; 1931,; 1969; includes Sep 3 1922 issue of The World Magazine (Oversize 2)
  - Maps - Provincetown Period (1921-1932), undated; 1926,; 1958; includes description from F. C. Waugh; emphasis on Cape Cod (Oversize 2)
  - New York Tribune, Oct 1918; newspaper prints -- caricatures of German Leaders (Oversize 2)
  - New York World magazine, 1922; includes drawings from F.C. Waugh (Oversize 2)
  - One Hundred Years of Growing with Provincetown, circa 1954 (Box 1)
  - Prints of flowers, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Prints of maps, undated; 1928,; 1930,; 1935,; 1958; includes maps of Florida; Old Cape Cod; Parts Unknown; Saint Pauls School, Concord, New Hampshire; Hudson River; New York; Long Island and the Coast of Connecticut (Oversize 2)
  - Ship prints and pictures, prints of ships; Provincetown Period, 1921-1932 (Oversize 2)
  - Textile designs, magazine reproduction of, 1919-1920; includes Bruno's Garret, Bruno's Weekly and assorted textiles (Map-case 1, Drawer 107)
  - Yankee Magazine-Pictures of House in Provincetown, Mass., 1965 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940-1971; includes F.C. Waugh exhibition information and other exhibition information (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Motivations, undated; typescript (Box 2)
  - Notebook, 1913-1919; includes drawings, photos and poems (Box 2)
  - Notes on navigation, circa 1928; includes additional typed and handwritten notes (Box 2)